And here's the pickle: "And because you belong to them, I returned my hands and left you." (Laughter) Translate that for me. (Applause) So, what have we done to protect the Arabic language? We turned this into a concern of the civil society, and we launched a campaign to preserve the Arabic language. Even though many people told me, "Why do you bother? Forget about this headache and go have fun." No problem! The campaign to preserve Arabic launched a slogan that says, "I talk to you from the East, but you reply from the West." We didn't say, "No! We do not accept this or that." We didn't adopt this style because that way, we wouldn't be understood. And when someone talks to me that way, I hate the Arabic language. We say-- (Applause) We want to change our reality, and be convinced in a way that reflects our dreams, aspirations and day-to-day life. In a way that dresses like us and thinks like we do. So, "I talk to you from the East, but you reply from the West" has hit the spot. Something very easy, yet creative and persuasive. After that, we launched another campaign with scenes of letters on the ground. You've seen an example of it outside, a scene of a letter surrounded by black and yellow tape with "Don't kill your language!" written on it. Why? Seriously, don't kill your language. We really shouldn't kill our language. If we were to kill the language, we'd have to find an identity. We'd have to find an existence. We'd go back to the beginning. This is beyond just missing our chance of being modern and civilized. After that we released photos of guys and girls wearing the Arabic letter. Photos of "cool" guys and girls. We are very cool! And to whoever might say, "Ha! You used an English word!" I say, "No! I adopt the word 'cool.'" Let them object however they want, but give me a word that's nicer and matches the reality better. I will keep on saying "Internet" I wouldn't say: "I'm going to the world wide web" (Laughs) Because it doesn't fit! We shouldn't kid ourselves. But to reach this point, we all have to be convinced that we shouldn't allow anyone who is bigger or thinks they have any authority over us when it comes to language, to control us or make us think and feel what they want. Creativity is the idea. So, if we can't reach space or build a rocket and so on, we can be creative. At this moment, every one of you is a creative project. Creativity in your mother tongue is the path. Let's start from this moment. Let's write a novel or produce a short film. A single novel could make us global again. It could bring the Arabic language back to being number one. So, it's not true that there's no solution; there is a solution! But we have to know that, and be convinced that a solution exists, that we have a duty to be part of that solution. In conclusion, what can you do today? Now, tweets, who's tweeting? Please, I beg of you, even though my time has finished, either Arabic, English, French or Chinese. But don't write Arabic with Latin characters mixed with numbers! (Applause) It's a disaster! That's not a language. You'd be entering a virtual world with a virtual language. It's not easy to come back from such a place and rise. That's the first thing we can do. Second, there are many other things that we can do. We're not here today to convince each other. We're here to bring attention to the necessity of preserving this language. Now I will tell you a secret. A baby first identifies its father through language. When my daughter is born, I'll tell her, "This is your father, honey (Arabic)." I wouldn't say, "This is your dad, honey (English)." And in the supermarket, I promise my daughter Noor, that if she says to me, "Thanks (Arabic)," I won't say, "Dis, 'Merci, Maman,'" and hope no one has heard her. (Applause) Let's get rid of this cultural cringe.
Y aquí viene el lío: "pero como eres suyo retiré la mano y te dejé" (Risas) Traduzcan eso. (Aplausos) ¿Qué hacemos entonces para proteger la lengua árabe? Llevamos la cuestión al nivel de la sociedad civil y lanzamos una campaña para preservar la lengua árabe. aunque mucha gente nos decía: "¿qué más da?" "Diviértanse, no se preocupen tanto". ¡No pasa nada! Nuestra campaña tenía por lema: "Te hablo desde Oriente y me respondes desde Occidente". No dijimos: "no vamos a aceptar esto, porque esta es nuestra lengua, etc". No usamos ese estilo porque no creemos que deba hacerse así, si alguien me habla así odiaría la lengua árabe. Decimos.... (Aplausos) Queremos ver cómo vivimos nuestra realidad de una manera similar a nuestros sueños, nuestro día a día, nuestros anhelos, de una manera que vista nuestra ropa, que piense como nosotros. Nuestro lema "Te hablo desde Oriente y me respondes desde Occidente", pone el dedo en la llaga, es sencillo, creativo y convincente. Después empezamos otra campaña, pusimos letras en la calle, (a lo mejor las vieron ahí fuera) y alrededor de ellas una cinta policial en la que decía: "¡No mates tu lengua!". ¿Por qué? De verdad, no debemos matar nuestra lengua. Entre todos debemos evitar matar nuestra lengua. Porque si la matamos, cuando volvamos en busca de nuestra identidad, cuando volvamos en busca de nuestra existencia, tendremos que volver a empezar desde cero, no solo no seremos capaces de ser modernos y desarrollados. También tomamos fotos de chicos y chicas vestidos con letras árabes. Fotos de chicos y chicas "cool". ¡Nosotros somos muy "cool"! Habrá quien diga: "Has usado una palabra inglesa, ¡te atrapamos!" No, he adoptado la palabra "cool". Les reto a encontrar una palabra más bella y más adecuada. Seguiré diciendo "Internet", y no "red de redes". (Risas) ¡No vale igual! ¿Es broma o qué? Pero para llegar a este punto tenemos que estar todos convencidos. No queremos dejar al más fuerte, al que cree tener el poder sobre la lengua, que nos domine y nos obligue a pensar y sentir como él quiere. La clave está en la creatividad. Si no podemos llegar al espacio o construir un cohete, podemos crear. En este momento, cada uno de Uds. es un proyecto creativo. La creatividad en la lengua materna es el camino Empecemos ahora, desde este momento. Escribamos una novela, rodemos un corto. Una sola novela puede dar la vuelta al mundo, puede devolver la lengua árabe a lo más alto. No digan que no hay solución. ¡Por supuesto que la hay! Tenemos que estar convencidos de que hay solución, y tenemos que ser parte de ella. Para terminar, ¿qué se puede hacer desde hoy? ¿Quién de aquí tiene Twitter? Por favor, se lo suplico, aunque mi tiempo se agote, en árabe, o en inglés, o en francés o en chino. ¡Pero no escriban árabe usando letras latinas y números! (Aplausos) ¡Eso es un desastre! ¡No es ninguna lengua! Es un mundo virtual, una lengua virtual y ya nadie nos podrá sacar de ahí. Eso es lo primero que podemos hacer. Segundo, hay muchas cosas que podemos hacer. Nosotros no estamos aquí para convencer a nadie, sino para advertir de que debemos cuidar nuestra lengua. Ahora les contaré un secreto. Cuando nace un niño, la primera manera con que conoce a su padre es la lengua. Así que cuando nazca mi hija le diré: "Este es papá, mi vida". [árabe] Y no le diré: "This is your dad, honey". Y en el supermercado, cuando mi hija Nour dé las gracias en árabe no le diré: "Dit merci !", deseando que nadie la hubiera escuchado. (Aplausos) Superemos este complejo frente a lo extranjero.